Qualifications and research interests_

Highly effective and experienced executive in Computational System Biology and Machine Learning. Extensive experience in biotech/pharma in the development and implementation of computational tools for multi omics data analysis, drug discovery, and target identification. I am interested in the application of computational tools in the drug discovery, disease biology characterization, large data analytics for biology, while focusing on bridging the gap between the wet and dry labs through highly engaging and fruitful collaborations.

Technical Skills ____

Machine learning | Deep learning | Multi-omics data analyses | R/Bioconductor | Python | AWS | Git

Education_

Virginia Polytechnic Institute and State University

Blacksburg, VA

Ph.D. in Genetics, Bioinformatics, and Computational Biology

Faculdade de Ciencias da Universidade de Lisboa

Lisboa, Portugal

B. Sc. in Biochemistry

Experience _____

Cellarity Boston, MA

Vice President, Computational and Data Sciences

July 2022 - February 2024

Cellarity is leading the discovery of novel chemical entities that can modulate cell behavior phenotypes through single cell technologies. In my role:

- Core member of R&D Leadership Team
- Implementation of vision, strategy, and operational framework for department
- Lead team of computational biologists, machine learning, and data scientists to deliver against program objectives
- Lead of PLatform Core Team, setting strategic and operational frameworks for the implementation of Cellarity computational platform
- Interfacing with external partners, board members, and founding VC partners on computational approaches at Cellarity

Rheos Medicines

Boston, MA
Senior Director Computational Biology and Bioinformatics

November 2020 - Make 2023

Senior Director, Computational Biology and Bioinformatics

November 2020 - July 2022

Rheos was a Precision Medicine company focused on integrating multi-omics data (transcriptomics and metabolomics) in the identification of novel targets for auto-immune disorders. In my role:

- Led implementattion of MetPM platform, Rheos' computational platform for precision medicine
- Implementation of Computational Biology and Bioinformatics strategy within the company
- Development of novel algorithm for patient stratification based on metabolic pathway representations
- Cross-functional integration of Computational Biology into programs at different stages of development
- Managed interactions with computational CROs to ensure on time delivery of work
- Led and managed relationships with ML CROs for implementation of Rheos' Knowledge Graph
- Communication of computational developments to board members, founding VC partners, and corporate partners

Wyss Institute @ Harvard University

APRIL 2024

Boston, MA

1

Lead, Predictive BioAnalytics Initiative, Advanced Technology Team

July 2016 - November 2020

The Wyss Institute of Harvard University is focusing on translating discoveries done in the lab into tangible applications. In my role:

- Founding member of the Predictive BioAnalytics Initiative
- Developed and implemented the research strategy for the Initiative, focusing on enabling ML/AI capabilities
- Managed and mentored staff scientists, post-doctoral fellows, graduate students, and interns
- Secure research funding through federal grants with DARPA, NIH
- Hands-on development of algorithms and computational approaches

Evelo BiosciencesSenior Scientist, Computational Systems Biology Lead

Cambridge, MA January 2015 - April 2016

As the lead Computational Systems Biologist at Evelo Biosciences, I was involved in the build out of the computational capabilities of the company, in support of preclinical development of microbiome-focused therapeutics for oncology. Some of the functions of the role included:

- Implementation of diverse tools for analysis of high throughput data (transcriptomics, RNA-seq, metabolomics) as well as a 16S rDNA sequencing analysis pipeline
- Responsible for the identification of novel therapeutic opportunities based on in-house and publicly available
- Implementation of analytical software tools to be used by bench scientists in R Shiny
- Responsible for the interface with IT provider to delineate and expand computational capabilities of the company, from general to research needs

Ember Therapeutics

Cambridge, MA

Principal Scientist, Computational Systems Biology Lead

January 2014 - December 2014

At Ember Therapeutics I was the Computational Systems Biology lead, where I oversaw the implementation and deployment of novel analytical tools for the identification of novel target opportunities for increased energy expenditure, not only from publicly available data but also from data coming from internal efforts. Some of the functions of the role included:

- Responsible for the implementation of diverse tools for analysis of high throughput data (transcriptomics, RNA-seq, metabolomics)
- Implementation of a knowledge based and data driven construction of screening libraries for recombinant proteins, small peptides, and RNAi therapeutic efforts
- Implementation of analytical strategies (QC, statistical analyses, hit-calling) for high throughput screens
- Responsible for the interface with IT provider to delineate and expand computational capabilities of the company, from general to research needs

Pfizer, IncSenior Research Scientist, Computational Sciences Center of Emphasis

Cambridge, MA

January 2011 - January 2014

I was a member of the Computational Sciences Center of Emphasis at Pfizer, providing computational support across different preclinical programs at the organization, from cardiovascular disease to pain management and drug repositioning efforts. Some of the functions of the role included:

- Development and implementation of a network analysis tool for the characterization of differential networks in healthy and diseased populations under the scope of metabolic diseases
- Implementation of network inference tools for the analysis of large-scale data sets
- Development and implementation of a methodology for metabolite set enrichment analysis for metabolomics data
- Performed data analysis in transcriptomics, proteomics and metabolomics for different partners within the organization with particular emphasis in Cardiovascular and Metabolic diseases

Howard Hughes Medical Institute @ Boston University

Boston, MA

Post-doctoral Fellow

July 2007 - January 2011

Post-doctoral training with Dr. James Collins at Boston University, focusing on the application of machine learning and network inference approaches in biomedicine.

DIOGO M. CAMACHO · CURRICULUM VITAE

Awards and Grants

Molecular circuits in the hematopoietic stem cell niche (NIH)

\$415,000 9/1/20

co-Investigator

Publications

- Valeri, JA, Soenksen, LR, Collins, KM, Ramesh, P, Cai, G, Powers, R, Angenent–Mari, NA, Camacho, DM, Wong, F, Lu, TK, Collins, JJ (2023), BioAutoMATED: An end-to-end automated machine learning tool for explanation and design of biological sequences, *Cell Systems*, 14, 525 [PubMed]
- Gazzaniga, FS, Camacho, DM, Wu, M, Palazzo, MFS, Dinis, ALM, Grafton, FN, Cartwright, MJ, Super, M, Kasper, DL, Ingber, DE (2021), Harnessing Colon Chip technology to identify commensal bacteria that promote host tolerance to infection, Frontiers in Cellular and Infection Microbiology, 11, 105 [PubMed]
- Sperry, MM, Novak, R, Keshari, V, Dinis, ALM, Cartwright, MJ, Camacho, DM, Paré, JF, Super, M, Levin, M, Ingber, DE (2022), Enhancers of host immune tolerance to bacterial infection discovered using linked computational and experimental approaches, Adv Sci [PubMed]
- Bein, A, ,Fadel, CW, Swenor, B, Cao, W, Powers, RK, **Camacho, DM**, Naziripour, A, Parsons, AW, LoGrande, NT, Sharma, S, Kim, S, Jalili-Firoozinezhad, S, Grant, J, Breault, DT, Iqbal, J, Ali, A, Denson, LA, Moore, SR, Prantil-Baun, R, Goyal, G, Ingber, DE (2022), Nutritional deficiency recapitulates intestinal injury associated with environmental enteric dysfunction in patient-derived Organ Chips, *Nature Biomed Eng* [PubMed]
- Bojar, D, Powers, RK, **Camacho, DM**, Collins, JJ (2020), Deep-Learning Resources for Studying Glycan-Mediated Host-Microbe Interactions, *Cell Host & Microbe*, 29, 132-144 [PubMed]
- Valeri, J, Collins, KM, Ramesh, P, Alcantar, M, Lepe, BA, Lu, TK, **Camacho, DM** (2020), Sequence-to-function deep learning frameworks for engineered riboregulators, *Nature Communications*, 11, 5058 [PubMed]
- Jalili-Firoozinezhad, S, Gazzaniga, FS, Calamari, EL, Camacho, DM, Fadel, C, Nestor, B, Cronce, MJ, Tovaglieri, A, Levy, O, Gregory, KE, Breault, DT, Cabral, JMS, Kasper, DL, Novak, R, Ingber, DE (2019), A complex human gut microbiome cultured in an anaerobic intestine-on-a-chip, *Nature Biomedical Engineering*, 3, 520-531 [PubMed]
- Tovaglieri, A, Sontheimer-Phelps, A, Geirnaert, A, Prantil-Baun, R, Camacho, DM, Chou, DB, Jalili-Firoozinezhad, S, de Wouters, T, Kasendra, M, Super, M, Cartwright, M, Richmond, CA, Breault, DT, Lacroix, C, Ingber, DE (2019), Species-specific enhancement of enterohemorrhagic *E. coli* pathogenesis mediated by microbiome metabolites, *Microbiome*, 7, 43 [PubMed]
- Camacho, DM, Collins, KM, Powers, RK, Costello, JC, Collins, JJ (2018), Next-generation machine learning for biological networks, *Cell*, 173, 1581-1592 [PubMed]
- Musah, S, Dimitrakakis, N, Camacho, DM, Church, GM, Ingber, DE (2018), Directed differentiation of human induced pluripotent stem cells into mature kidney podocytes and establishment of a Glomerulus Chip, Nature Protocols, 13, 1662-1685 [PubMed]
- Paandey, SP, Winkler, JA, Li, H, **Camacho, DM**, Collins, JJ, Walker, GC (2014), Central role for RNase YbeY in Hfq-dependent and Hfq-independent small-RNA regulation in bacteria, *BMC Genomics*, 15, 121 [PubMed]
- Galagan, JE, Minch, K, Peterson, M, Lyubetskya, A, Azzizi, E, Sweet, L, Gomes, A, Rustad, T, Dolganov, G, Glotova, I, Abeel, T, Mawhinney, C, Kennedy, A, Allard, R, Brabant, W, Krueger, A, Jaini, S, Honda, B, Yu, W-H, Hickey, M, Zucker, J, Garay, C, Weiner, B, Sisk, P, Stolte, C, Winkler, J, Van de Peer, Y, Iazzetti, P, Camacho, D, Dreyfuss, J, Liu, Y, Dorhoi, A, Mollenkopf, H-J, Drogaris, P, Lamontagne, J, Zhou, Y, Piquenot, J, Park, ST, Raman, S, Kaufmann, S, Mohney, R, Chelsky, D, Moody, B, Sherman, D, Schoolnik, G (2013), The Mycobacterium tuberculosis regulatory network and hypoxia, *Nature*, 499, 178-183 [PubMed]
- Belenky, P, Camacho, D, Collins, JJ (2013), Fungicidal drugs induce a common oxidative-damage cellular death pathway, Cell Reports, 3, 350-358 [PubMed]
- Marbach, D, Costello, JC, Kuffner, R, Vega, N, Prill, RJ, Camacho, DM, Allison, KR, the DREAM5 Consortium, Kellis, M, Collins, JJ, Stolovitzky, G (2012), Wisdom of crowds for robust gene network inference, *Nature Methods*, 9, 796-804 [PubMed]
- Dwyer, DJ, **Camacho, DM**, Callura, JM, Kohanski, MA, Collins, JJ (2011), Antibiotic-induced bacterial cell death exhibits physiological and biochemical hallmarks of apoptosis, *Molecular Cell*, 46, 561-572 [PubMed]
- Modi, SR, Camacho, DM, Kohanski, MA, Collins, JJ (2011), Functional characterization of bacterial sRNAs using a network biology approach, *Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA*, 108, 15522-15527 [PubMed]
- Camacho, DM, Collins, JJ (2009), Systems biology strikes gold, Cell, 137, 24-26 [PubMed]
- **Camacho, D**, Vera-Licona, P, Laubenbacher, R, Mendes, P (2007), Comparison of existing reverse engineering methods by use of an in silico system, *Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci.*, 1115, 73-89 [PubMed]
- Mendes, P, Camacho, D, de la Fuente, A (2005), Modelling and simulation for metabolomics data analysis, Biochem. Soc. Trans., 33, 1427-1429 [PubMed]

- **Camacho, D**, de la Fuente, A, Mendes, P (2005), The origin of correlations in metabolomics data, *Metabolomics*, 1, 53-63 [Link]
- Martins, AM, **Camacho, D**, Shuman, J, Sha, W, Mendes, P, Shulaev, V (2004), A systems biology study of two distinct growth phases of *Saccharomyces cerevisiae* cultures, *Curr. Genomics*, 5, 649-663 [Link]

Patents.

- Novak, R, Jalili-Firoozinezhad, S, Gazzaniga, FS, Calamari, EL, Camacho, DM, Nestor, BA, Fadel, C, Cronce, ML, Kasper, DL, Ingber, DE, Bein, A, Complex Human Gut Microbiome Cultured in an Anaerobic Human Gut-on-A-Chip, US20240002808A1 (2023)
- Driggers, EM, Soh, K, **Camacho DM**, Transcriptional subseetting of patient cohorts based on metabolic pathway activity (*submitted*)
- Garruss, AS, Church, GM, **Camacho, DM**, Riboregulators and methods of use thereof (submitted)
- Soenksen, LR, **Camacho, DM**, Collins, KM, Angenent-Mari, NM, Garruss, AS, Collins, JJ, Church, GM, Method for deep learning for RNA synthetic biology (*submitted*)
- Collins, JJ, Belenky, P, Camacho, DM (2015), Compositions and methods for treating fungal infections, WO2014130922A